Guide to the Edwards Amasa Park Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Edwards Amasa Park papers
1835-1899
RG 291
Yale University Divinity School Library
9
(20 boxes)
The papers primarily document Park's work as Professor of Sacred Rhetoric (1836-1847) and Professor of Christian Theology (1847 to 1881) at Andover Theological Seminary, and as editor of Bibliotheca Sacra from 1844 to 1884.
Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1808 December 29 Born in Providence, RI
1826 Graduated from Brown University
1827 Principal, classical schools, Weymouth & Braintree, MA
1831 Received B.D. from Andover Thelogical Seminary
1831 December 21 Ordained as Congregational minister
1831-1834 Colleague Pastor with Richard S. Storrs, First Church, Braintree, MA
1835-1836 Professor of Mental and Moral Philosophy; Hebrew Literature, Amherst College, MA
1836-1847 Professor of Sacred Rhetoric, Andover Theological Seminary
1847-1881 Professor of Christian Theology, Andover Theological Seminary
1844-1884 Editor, Bibliotheca Sacra
1900 June 4 Died in Andover, MA
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School, 2017
Scope and Contents
The Edwards Amasa Park Papers, 1835-1899, document the professional work of Park. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: correspondence, sermons, lectures, notes on theological subjects, notes on readings, miscellaneous notes (fragments), student questions, newspaper clippings, and association items.
The correspondence is business and personal in nature, although much of the material relates to Park's work as editor of Bibliotheca Sacra. There is a name index to the correspondence available in the orignal finding aid for the collection, available at the repository.
The lecture notes are arranged according to order for a theological system prescribed by Park and described in document titled Syllabus of Lectures. This document is not written in Park's hand, but was almost certainly dictated by him. The document does contain revisions in Park's hand.
There is one document case of material which is arbitrarily assigned the category of association items. These items were found with unprocessed Park papers. The documents are not in his hand; and there is no readily apparent way to link them with other material in the collection. This group consists of a small number of letters and miscellaneous manuscripts.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence
II. Sermons
III. Lectures
IV. Notes and Clippings
V. Association Items.
Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900; Andover Theological Seminary
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  For a full list of letters and name index see the original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Fragments and undated correspondence, No date (Box 1)
  - Dated correspondence, 1848 - 1874 May (Box 1)
    Correspondence is primarily to Parks. For a full list of letters see original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton. Correspondents include David Fosdick, Jr., Leonard Bacon, R. S. Storrs, Increase N. Tarbox, Samuel Hopkins.
  - Dated correspondence, 1874 June - 1877 (Box 2)
  - Dated correspondence, 1878 January - July (Box 3)
  - Dated correspondence, 1878 August - 1879 May (Box 4)
  - Dated correspondence, 1879 June - 1880 May (Box 5)
  - Dated correspondence, 1880 June - 1881 April (Box 6)
  - Dated correspondence, 1881 May - 1882 (Box 7)
  - Dated correspondence, 1883–1889 (Box 8)
- Sermons, Series II
  - Sermon delivered in the church at Lawrence South, No date (Box 9)
  - Undated sermons arranged by text, No date (Box 9)
  - Dated sermons, 1835–1856 (Box 9)
- Lectures, Series III
  - Bound set of notes
    - Volume 1: Existence of God, Attributes of God, Authority of the Bible (Box 10)
    - Volume 2: Authority of the Bible (continued), Trinity (Box 10)
    - Volume 3: Government of God, Divine Decree, Will, Ability, Motive (Box 10)
    - Volume 4: Moral Agency, Depravity (Box 10)
    - Volume 5: Depravity (continued), Virtue (Box 10)
    - Volume 6: Atonement, Regeneration, 1852, no date (Box 10)
    - Volume 7: Regeneration (continued), Space (Box 10)
  - Loose lecture notes
    - "Syllabus of Lectures" (Box 11)
    - I. Virtue/Depravity: I volume "Notes on ethics"; 1 folder notes on depravity (Box 11)
    - II. God: 1 volume "Theology for Bible classes of youthful students"; 1 volume "Notes on the existence and attributes of God"; 1 volume "Nature of God"; 1 folder "Christian doctrine of God" (parts 3-4) (Box 11)
    - III. Bible: 2 volumes "The Bible" (Box 12)
    - IV. 2 volumes "Trinity"; 2 folders: "Trinity", "Remarks on the difficulties in the way of apprehending the doctrine of the union of two consciousnesses in the God-man", 1880, no date (Box 12)
    - V. Government of God: 1. on causes, etc., 2. "Unity of the created system" (Box 12)
    - VII. Sin (Box 12)
    - VIII. Atonement: 1 volume "The atonement"; folders: 1. papers on the union of Christ with his friends, 2. same as 1., 3. papers on the moral influence of the atonement, 4. "General reply to the misunderstandings of use, and Objections to the governmental theory of the atonement", 5. "Causes of Christ's sufferings", 6. 11 Atonement scenic", 7. Jonathan Edwards Jr. on the atonement, 8. Timothy Dwight on the atonement, 9. Schauffler on inspiration and atonement, 10. notes, 11. "The governmental theory of the atonement", 1868, 1880, no date (Box 13)
    - X. Sanctification: 1 volume miscellaneous notes on sanctification, 1 volume "Notes on faith" (Box 13)
    - XIV. Church: 1 volume "Church" (Box 14)
- Notes and Clippings, Series IV
  - Notes on theological subjects
    Arranged alphabetically by title; all are notebooks unless otherwise indicated
    - 1. "atonement"; 2. loose notes on atonement (11 folders ) (Box 14)
    - 3. "commonplace book" ( 2 volumes) (Box 15)
    - 4. "Definitions on Theology", 5. depravity--"Report of the Deaf-Mutes with Remarks" (3 folders - Deals with issue of whether or not deaf-mutes can have religious knowledge), 6. "Dr. Willmer's Dogmatics and also, Thoughts on Philosophy and Theology, Realism and Nominalism", 7. "Formative Principles" 3 folders, 8. "Introduction to Theology11 /"Notes"; 9. "Miscellany Booklett II", 10. "Notes Principally on Space and Time" (Box 16)
    - 11. "Qualifications of a Pastor", 12. "Remarks on Space &c. A few pages on Edwards", 13. "Thoughts on Philosophy and Theology", 14. "Thoughts on the Trinity", 15. "Trinity" (Box 17)
    - 16. "Trinity Booklet I", 17 "Trinity. Edwards" (Box 18)
  - Notes on readings
    - 1. [Bushnell], 2. "Dr. Willmer's Dogmatics" (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - "Mr. Burquet's Classification" (1 volume), "Index to Miscellany" (2 volumes) (Box 18)
  - Other notes
    - Loose miscellaneous notes (8 folders) (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous papers--non-theological (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Student questions (Box 19)
    - Bound volume of notes by student on Parks' lecture on Homiletics (Box 20)
    - Newspaper clippings (arranged by subject) (Box 19)
      1. atonement, 2. the Bible, 3. christology, 4. doctrine/creeds, 5. eschatology, 6. evangelization, 7. evolution, science and theology, 8. God, 9. justification/sanctification, 10. liberalism/the "New Theology", 11. and 12. the Lord's Supper, 13. Lutheranism and Calvinism, 14. miscellaneous, 15. Park, 16. theology/philosophy, 17. unitarianism
- Association Items, Series V
  - Letters
    - Undated letters from J. W. Edwards, and L. L. Robbins (Box 19)
    - Mrs. H. D. Ketchel to -- McKean; from Middlebury, VT, 1873 (Box 19)
    - F. A. Reed to -- Draper; from Concord, [?];; Prof. Edw. Wiebe to A.S. Barnes & Co.; from Hamburg, Germany, 1877 (Box 19)
    - A. M. Fairbairn to -- Duff; from Bradford, [?], 1878 (Box 19)
    - N. V. Hull to Warren F. Draper; from Alfred Center, NY, 1879 (Box 19)
    - Yung Wing to -- Lane; from Avon, GT, 1881 (Box 19)
    - to -- Witherow from Philadelphia, PA; Charles A. Aiken to William --; from Princeton, NJ, 1882 (Box 19)
    - to W. H. Warren; from New Haven, CT, 1883 (Box 19)
    - R. Henry Davis to Rev. W. DeLors; from Nugata, Japan, 1886 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous manucripts
    - 1. Abschnitt aus der Dogmatik von Prof; Julius Muller, 2. Clark, John C. History of alphabets. April, 1874, 3. Dr. Smyth's theory of the Atonement ... (document related to Andover Controversy?), 4. Dogmatik von C. R. F. Muller, 5. Eastman, Mary D. notebook of poetry (Box 19)
    - 6. Extracts from a letter of Dr. Bushnell to Dr. Hawes, dated April 3, 1854, 7. Hermann Christian Karl Friedrich Hupfel, Doctor of Philosophy and Theology, at the University of Halle, 8. Moral van C. R. Tholuck, 9. notes (Box 19)
    - 10. Park, Harrison G. extract from 22 Dec. 1820 sermon of D. Webster, Plymouth, Ma, dated 30 Jan. 1821, 11. Potio.in, Lemuel S. Nine Propositions on the Philosophy of the Atonement, 12. Syllabus for a System of Theology, ,13. Theologia Dogmatica. Halle: Semester October till March 1854-55. Dr. Julius Muller (Box 19)